Mss.530.1.Ar2.2 Mss.530.1.Ar2.2
American Philosophical Society
J. H. (John Hasbrouck) Van Vleck papers, 1923-1959
Mss.530.1.Ar2.2
American Philosophical Society
189.0 Item(s)
These contain a few notes and memoranda by Van Vleck, but the bulk of the collection is letters to and from him. Correspondents include Raymond T. Birge, Gerhard H. Dieke, Paul A. M. Dirac, Edwin C. Kemble, and Robert S. Mulliken.
189 items.
Van Vleck, J. H., (John Hasbrouck), 1899-1980
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by J. H. Van Vleck and accessioned, 1964.
General note
This collection forms part of the Archives for the History of Quantum Physics, for which a complete listing appears in "Sources for the History of Quantum Physics," edited by Thomas S. Kuhn, et al. (Philadelphia, 1967).
Biographical/Historical note
J. H. Van Vleck was a physicist.
Dieke, Gerhard Heinrich, 1901-1965; Kemble, Edwin C., (Edwin Crawford), 1889-1984; Education; Educational Material; Notebooks; Physics.; Quantum theory.; Science and Technology
- Papers, 1923-1959; Van Vleck, J. H., (John Hasbrouck), 1899-1980
  Scope and Contents note
  D. 189 items. Various sizes. Presented to the Archive for the History of Quantum Physics by Van Vleck;1964.
  - Summary, paragraph by paragraph, of Bohr's "Uber die Anwendung de Quanten-theorie auf den Atomban...", July?, 1923; 8-3/4x5-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    A.D. 4p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics,No.2.)
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., March 22, 1924; 10-1/2x8; Foote, Paul D. (Paul Darwin), 1888-
    Washington, Typed L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning his paper:The Quantum Theory of Line Spectra" with comments by Ruark. Suggestions for its publication in the Bulletin of the National Research Council.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., March 22, 1924; 10-1/2x8; Ruark, Arthur Edward, 1899-
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and enc.of pp.1-16,19-33. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Encloses his comments on the article: "The Quantum theory of Line Spectra." at the request to Foote.
  - Letter to [John S.] Van [Vleck], July 27, 1924; 7x4-1/2; Slater, John C. (John Clarke), 1900-1976
    A.L.S. 12p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) His work in physics for the year with Bohr and Kramers and his comments on them. Refers to Urey as a fellow student.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., Aug. 29, 1924; 10-1/2x8; Kemble, Edwin C. (Edwin Crawford), 1889-
    Cambridge, Mass., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Comments on his paper and work on the correspondence principle for absorption.
  - Letter to [Hendrik Anthony] Kramers, Sept. 22, [1924]; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L.with 1p. in A.L. 3p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning dispersion formula and his work on the quantum theory of line spectra Needs comments of Bohr on Rydberg formula.
  - Letter to Paul D. Foote, Washington, D.C., Sept. 24, 1924; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No. 2.) Questions concerning footnotes of his bulletin on quantum physics.
  - Letter to John H. Van Vleck, Oct. 24, 1924; Born, Max, 1882-1970
    A.L.S. 1p. in German.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, Nov. 11, 1924; 11x8-1/2; Kramers, Hendrik Anthony, 1894-1952
    Copenhagen, A.L.S. 3p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics.No.2.) Concerning the absorption and dispersion formulae. "Motion [in atoms"...can not be described by mechanics." Refers to work done by Slater, Einstein, Planck and Bohr.
  - Letter to M[ax] Born, Göttingen, Ger., Nov. 13, 1924; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Their articles on dispersion and absorption formulae. Quantum physics.
  - Letter to Paul D. Foote, Washington, D.C., Nov. 21, 1924; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Sorry he is taking so long to get his paper ready for publication. Quantum theory.
  - Letter to H[endrik] A[nthony] Kramers, Copenhagen, Den., Nov. 30, 1924; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 4p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Agrees with him rather than with Becker on the correspondence principles for absorption and dispersion.
  - Letter to E[dwin] C. Kemble, Cambridge, Mass., Dec. 1, 1924; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning atomic theory. His work goes slowly.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van [Vleck], Dec. 8, 1924; 11x8-1/2; Slater, John C. (John Clarke), 1900-1976
    Cambridge, Mass., Typed L.S. 4p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No..2.) Concerning his paper on correspondence principles. His work on polarization of resonance radiation.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. VanVleck, Minneapolis, Minn., Dec. 10, 1924; 10-1/2x8; Kemble, Edwin C. (Edwin Crawford), 1889-
    Cambridge, Mass., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Questions on inner quantum numbers. Physics. Refers to Slater.
  - Letter to E[dwin] C. Kemble, Cambridge, Mass., Dec. 15, 1924; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Comments on study on "the states of maximum inter quantum numbers should be those of minimum energy."
  - Letter to John C. Slater, Cambridge, Mass., Dec. 15, 1924; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 2p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Discusses his problem and has tried to include it in the Correspondence Principle of Dispersion. Will discuss it with him.
  - Letter to Paul D. Foote, Washington, D.C., Jan. 28, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Minneapolis, Minn., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Questions for the publication of his paper and his just finished a section on the "dynamical technique of the quantum theory."
  - Letter to John O. Slater, Cambridge, Mass., Feb. 3, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning spatial quantization.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, June 16, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Cal., A.L.S. 4p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Questions on molecular energy.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, July 4, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Cal., A.L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Thanks for his help in developing his energy formula.
  - Letter to Paul D. Foote, Washington, D.C., Aug. 10, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Madison, Wisc., Typed L. 5p.and enc.of 7p. Carbon copy (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Forwards his manuscript: "Quantum Principles and Line-Spectra" and encloses some pages listing material which might be deleted. Comments on publication.
  - Letter to G[erhard] H. Dieke, Berkeley, Cal., Sept. 27, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 3p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Discusses questions in quantum physics.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, Oct. 9, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Dieke, Gerhard Heinrich, 1901-1965
    Berkeley, Typed L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning his paper on curves of specific molecules, calculated "on Einstein's suggestion."
  - Letter to Max Born, Gottingen, Ger., Oct. 19, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Incomplete. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Comments on his articles on excited molecules. Physics.
  - Letter to G[erhard] H. Dieke, Berkeley, Cal., Oct. 29, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning the study on curves and oscillations.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., Nov. 10, 1925; 10-1/2x8; Kemble, Edwin C. (Edwin Crawford), 1889-
    Cambridge, Mass., Typed L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning specific heat of hydrogen. Projected work of Slater on "alternating intensities in band spectra of gas molecules...of two similar atoms."
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., Nov. 20, [1925?]; 3-1/4x5-1/2; Foote, Paul D. (Paul Darwin), 1888-
    Washington, D.C., L.on postal card. 1p.and add. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning his proof for his work on line spectra.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., Nov. 25, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Born, Max, 1882-
    Cambridge, Mess., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Apologizes for errors in his text. Hopes to meet him to explain certain things about quantum physics.
  - Letter to Max Born, Cambridge, Mass., Dec. 5, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Hopes to invite him to lecture at Minnesota.
  - Letter to Paul D. Foote, Washington, D.C., Dec. 7, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning proof of his book. Would like to see such publications in hard bindings, even at additional cost.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., Dec. 10, [1925]; 3-1/4x5-1/2; Foote, Paul D. (Paul Darwin), 1888-
    Washington, D.C., A.L.on postal card. 1p.and add. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Doesn't believe the important publications can be bound at this time.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., Dec. 14, 1925; 11x8-1/2; Born, Max, 1882-
    Cambridge, Mass., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Can visit him in Chicago. Would like to lecture on the new quantum theory at Minneapolis.
  - Letter to Max Born, Cambridge, Mass., Jan. 8, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L.with ms.notes. 1p. Carbon copy (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning his lecture at Minnesota on quantum physics.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., Jan. 13, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Born, Max, 1882-
    Cambridge, Mass., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Has already filled his schedule and cannot lecture on quantum theory at Minnesota. Hopes they can meet.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van [Vleck], Jan. 25, 1926; 10-1/2x8; Breit, Gregory, 1899-
    Washington, D.C., A.L.S. 2p. (see Archives for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning quantum theory as worked out by Born and Fermi.
  - Letter to Paul D. Foote, Feb. 8, [1926?]; 7x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Telegram. 1p. Carbon copy "Approximate Copy." (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning his publication on quantum physics.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., Feb. 25, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Born, Max, 1882-
    Berkeley, Cal., Typed L.S. 1p (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Is to lecture on quantum theory at Madison, but would like to discuss things with him, personally.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, March 12, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Cal., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Asks him to write on quantum theory for the Optical Society of America. Physics.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, March 23, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Articles and work for committee on physical optics. Concerning work on quantum theory. Refers to Mulliken and Dieke.
  - Letter to E[dwin] C. Kemble, Cambridge, Mass., April 19, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Congratulates him on his Guggenheim. Concerning publications on quantum theory. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, May 1, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Dieke, Gerhard Heinrich, 1901-1965
    Berkeley, Cal., A.L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning a study on quantum of the hydrogen.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., May 5, 1926; 10-1/2x8; Dushman, Saul, b. 1883
    Schenectady, N.Y., Typed L. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics.No.2.) Compliments him on his publication on quantum principles. Wishes it had been better bound and printed.
  - Letter to E[dwin] C. Kimball [Kemble], Cambridge, Mass., May 10, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Hopes they can get cloth covers on his publication.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., June 1, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Cal., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics.No.2.) Thanks for the publication, and explain why he sold it. Concerning work for the Physical Optics committee.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, July 21, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Dennison, David Mathias, 1900-
    Ludington, Mich., A.L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics.No.2.) Is glad he is publishing on quantum theory for he thinks the more published, the better. Concerning dielectrics.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, Aug. 24, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Cal., Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning reports for the Physical Optics committee on various studies.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, Sept. 10, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Kronig, R. (Ralph), 1904-
    Chocorua, N.H., A.L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics.No.2.) Concerning his work on dielectrets.
  - Letter to [Raymond T.] Birge, Sept. 16, [1926]; 10-3/4x8-1/4; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 2p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning his syllabus on the new quantum mechanics and comments on it.
  - Letter to [Ralph de Laer] Kronig, Sept. 18, 1926; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 2p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning work on dielectric constants. Concerning atoms and molecular activity.
  - Letter to the members of the Committee on Physical Optics, Optical Society of America, Sept. 20, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Cal., Typed L.S. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Reports on what is to be printed, including Van Vleck's article on quantum theory.
  - Letter to the members of the Committee on Physical Optics, Optical Society of America, Sept. 23, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Typed L.S. 2p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Additional information on the forthcomin report on relativity, etc.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, Sept. 24, 1926; 10-1/2x8; Kronig, R. (Ralph), 1904-
    New York, N.Y., A.L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No. 2.) Concerning his study of rigid rotations of molecules; encloses carbon copy. For enclosure,see: Kronig. The Dielectric Constant...; [Sept. 1926].
  - Letter to R[aymond] T. Birge, Berkeley, Cal., Sept. 31, 1926; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 3p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning their report for the Optical Society, with comments on bibliography for quantum theory.
  - The dielectric constant of symmetrical polyatomic dipole-cases on the new quantum mechanics, Sept., 1926; 11x8-1/2; Kronig, R. (Ralph), 1904-
    Typed D. 6p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Enclosed originally in: Kronig to Van Vleck; Sept. 24, 1926.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, Oct. 7, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Cal., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning a publication on quantum physics for the Optical Society.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., Oct. 11, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Ingersoll, Leonard Rose, 1880-1958
    Madison, Wisc., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Congratulates him on his report on the new quantum theories.
  - Letter to the members of the Physical Optics Committee, Oct. 13, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Cal., Typed L.S. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for one History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning the publication on quantum physics.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., Oct. 29, 1926; 10-1/2x8; Kemble, Edwin C. (Edwin Crawford), 1889-
    Cambridge, Mass., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning studies on quantum physics and comments on them.
  - Letter to E[dwin] C. Kemble, Cambridge, Mass., Nov. 1, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 2p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Discusses various problems in quantum physics.
  - Letter to [Sir] C[harles] G. Darwin, Edinburgh, Scotland, Nov. 4, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning his work on lines.
  - Letter to the members of the Physical Optics Committee, Nov. 15, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archives for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Hopes their report will soon be out. Suggestions for proof-reading.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Minneapolis, Minn., Dec. 1, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Rodebush, Worth Huff, b. 1887
    Orbana, Ill., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archives for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Comments on studies on chemical constants.
  - Letter to E[dwin] C. Kemble, Cambridge, Mass., Dec. 1, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Suggests editorial changes for paper by Mulliken on quantum physics.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Dec. 10, 1926; 11-1/4x8-3/4; Rawlins, F. I. G. (Francis Ian Gregory), 1895-1969
    Cambridge, England, A.L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Asks for his publications on quantum physics and encloses his own.
  - Letter to J[ohn] H. Van Vleck, Madison, Wis., Dec. 20, 1926; 10-1/2x8; Kemble, Edwin C. (Edwin Crawford), 1889-
    Cambridge, Mass., Typed L. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics.No.2.) Concerning publications on the new quantum mechanics.
  - Letter to the members of the Physical Optics Committee, Dec. 28, 1926; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Cal., L.S. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning the publication and distribution of the Physical Optics report.
  - Letter to Arthur [Edward] Ruark, Pittsburg, Penna., Jan. 4, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 2p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Comments on his paper on quantum postulates.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, Jan. 15, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Cal., Typed L.S. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning their publication and problems in getting it off the press. Refers to Kemble and his publication.
  - Letter to Robert S. Mulliken, New York, Jan. 17, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 2p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Hopes he moves to Minnesota. Gives some new results on NO and O2 in quantum theory
  - Letter to Gregory Breit, Washington, D.C., Jan. 26, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L.S. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Thanks for loan of slides. Comments on Dr. Schroedinger who visits Washington.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, Jan., 1927; 10-3/4x8-1/2; Kramers, Hendrik Anthony, 1894-1952
    Utrecht, A.L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Recommends a young physicist, Niessen, for a post and comments on his work.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, Feb. 3, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Typed L.S. 2p. (See Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Several questions on line-spectra and quantum theory.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van [Vleck], Feb. 8, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Mulliken, Robert Sanderson
    New York, Typed L.S. 3p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Comments on work on No and O2. Quantum theory.
  - Letter to [John H.Van Vleck], Feb. 20, 1927; 11-1/2x8-3/4; Reiche, F. (Fritz), 1883-1969
    Breslau, Ger., A.L.S. 2p. In German. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Thanks for publication on line-spectra of the hydrogen atom. Some of his own experiments.
  - Letter to "Mully" [Robert S. Mulliken], Feb. 22, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 3p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Comments on his paper. Asks him to read a paper on quantum physics for him.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van [Vleck], Feb. 25, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Mulliken, Robert Sanderson
    New York, Typed L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning line-spectra.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, Feb. 27, 1927; 9x7; Darwin, Charles Galton, Sir, 1887-1962
    Edinburgh, A.L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Comments on, "The Electron as a Vector Wave" and theories on the atom.
  - Letter to the Secretary for Research Council Fellowships in Physics...,National Research Council, Washington, D.C., March 1, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics.No.2.) Recommends Oppenheimer for a fellowship
  - Letter to R[aymond] T. Birge, Berkeley, Cal., March 2, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Van Vleck, J. H. (John Hasbrouck), 1899-
    Typed L. 1p. Carbon copy. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Concerning the normal state of NO, as Mulliken states. Publications.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, March 5, 1927; 8-3/4x7; Kemble, Edwin C. (Edwin Crawford), 1889-
    Munich, Ger., A.L.S. 4p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) His work. Interest in NO and O2, and comments on them. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [John H.] Van Vleck, March 10, 1927; 11x8-1/2; Birge, Raymond T. (Raymond Thayer), 1887-
    Berkeley, Cal., Typed L.S. 2p. (see Archive for the History of Quantum Physics. No.2.) Considering his and Mulliken's work on line-spectra. Concerning Dirac and comments on his anti-American statements. Refers to Condon.